Today's דף Daf לז Lamed Zayin (57), we start in the middle
of סו עמוד ב Samech Vav Amud Bet at the two dots.
And after we've got with some of the details of how they
would actually roast the barley,
some before that talked about a little like popcorn in a like
a closed metal container. Anyway, now we turn to a different discussion
about חלה Challah and מעשרות. Ma'asrot. And we get a little bit
off the issue of מנחות Menachot and into some more classic discussions
that the גמרא Gemara has had. So the משנה Mishnah has taught
that the extra flour they would redeem and some people could buy
it and use it, and you would not give מעשר Ma'aser from
it but you would give חלה. Challah. The logic being that the
obligation of מעשר Ma'aser is defined at the moment of מירוח Miruach
of when the barley of when the grain is smoothed over in
the pile, and at that moment it was owned by the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash and הקדש, Hekdesh, so therefore it was exempt, whereas
the obligation of חלה Challah is defined at the moment when the
flour is added and when the dough is kneaded, and at that
moment it's no longer הקדש, Hekdesh, it's owned by the private individual.
So that makes a lot of sense. But then comes along רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and he says no, even you're חייב chayav not
only in חלה Challah but in מעשר Ma'aser as well. So let's
take a look. This is going to be the focus of the
גמרא Gemara for the entirety of today's דף. Daf. So רבי עקיבא
מחייב בחלה ובמעשר. Rabbi Akiva mechayev beChallah ubeMa'aser. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
says you're חייב chayav in חלה Challah and in מעשר. Ma'aser. So
אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, אמר רב כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana,
so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to explain רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva,
אומר היה רבי עקיבא, Omer haya Rabbi Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
used to say מירוח הקדש אינו פוטר, Miruach Hekdesh eino poter, that
the מירוח Miruach which is this smoothing of the grain pile done
by הקדש Hekdesh does not exempt. And that's a simple read of
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. He says that you get it after הקדש
Hekdesh has, you know, dealt with all of the grain and turned
it into flour and now you're still חייב chayav in מעשר. Ma'aser.
So whatever הקדש Hekdesh did did not exempt it. Now תוספות Tosafos
have a question. תוספות Tosafos says then how did הקדש Hekdesh ever
offer up this grain as a קרבן Korban if it was חייב
chayav in מעשר? Ma'aser? It was טבל, Tevel, you know, הקדש Hekdesh
isn't allowed you're not allowed as a קרבן Korban to do something
that's אסור assur to be eaten. So obviously it is exempt. It
is possible that the גמרא Gemara understands that while it's still owned
by הקדש, Hekdesh, it's exempt. But the fact that now a private
individual has now taken possession of it, the fact that הקדש Hekdesh
happened to have owned it at a particular stage does not, you
know, make it retain its exempt status. And now the person would
be obligated. So that's maybe a more nuanced way of saying רבי
עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but nevertheless this is the simple read of רבי
עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. It's nice that הקדש Hekdesh owned it at that
critical time, now you own it, you become חייב. chayav. Okay. וסמתיב
רב ששת, Ve'samtiv Rav Sheshet, רב ששת Rav Sheshet asked on this:
let's see if this really works. מותר של שלוש סאים, Motar shel
shalosh se'im, the remainder of the three סאים, se'im, מה היו עושין
בו? Mah hayu osin bo? What would they do with the remainder
of the three סאים? se'im? The amount that had turned into flour
that would not be needed for the עישרון isaron of the עומר?
Omer? So what would they do with it? מה היו עושין בו?
Mah hayu osin bo?
So נפדה ונאכל לכל אדם, nifdeh vene'echal lechol adam, so it would
be redeemed and could be eaten by anybody וחייב בחלה פטור מן
המעשרות. vechayav beChallah patur min hama'asrot. You would have to take חלה
Challah from it when you made it into dough, but you're exempt
from מעשרות, Ma'asrot, that's the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, who says so
the reason we said that the obligation of מעשר Ma'aser occurred at
the moment it was הקדש, Hekdesh, but the obligation but חלה Challah
occurs after you own it, so that's the split. רבי עקיבא מחייב
בחלה ובמעשר. Rabbi Akiva mechayev beChallah ubeMa'aser. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva makes
it obligated in חלה Challah and מעשר. Ma'aser. So so far it's
just our משנה. Mishnah. But now the ברייתא Baraita goes on: אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said to רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, פודה מיד
גזבר יוכיח, podeh miyad gizbar yochiach, I will prove that what you're
saying is wrong. If a normal person redeems the grain from redeems,
not this thing, redeems flour from the temple treasurer in another case.
The temple owns some flour and somebody redeemed it, what's the הלכה?
Halakha? So דחייב בחלה פטור מן המעשרות. dechayav beChallah patur min hama'asrot.
The הלכה Halakha is you're חייב chayav in חלה Challah because you
make חלה Challah after you redeemed it, but you're exempt from מעשרות
Ma'asrot because it became flour in the hand of הקדש. Hekdesh. So
there too, here as well, it should be the same הלכה, Halakha,
you should be חייב chayav in חלה Challah and exempt from מעשרות.
Ma'asrot. So the גמרא Gemara says, you know, isn't that exactly begging
the question? Like isn't that exactly what they're debating? They're saying, oh,
you say חייב chayav in both, I'll prove to you you're wrong,
if you get flour from הקדש Hekdesh you're חייב chayav in חלה
Challah but you're exempt from מעשרות. Ma'asrot. So the גמרא Gemara says
how is that not circular? So the גמרא Gemara says אם איתא,
im issa, if רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva position was really based on
a general principle that הקדש's Hekdesh owning does not exempt it from
מעשר, Ma'aser, דמירוח הקדש אינו פוטר, deMiruach Hekdesh eino poter, that the
that when הקדש Hekdesh owned it and it was had מירוח, Miruach,
the smoothing, it was not exempt from מעשר, Ma'aser, it didn't remain
exempt after you bought it, if it was a general principle, not
specific to עומר, Omer, מאי קאמרי ליה? mai kamre leih? What are
they trying to prove anyway? Hehe, that's exactly what they're debating, right?
So it's a very point, it's circular. So what the גמרא Gemara
says is since they're trying to prove to him by saying oh
look, normal person who buys flour, the הלכה's Halakha like we say,
it seems that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva admits what a normal case
is and that for some reason רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is treating
עומר Omer as a special case. So that's a pretty good proof.
So if that so now let's not try to assume רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva has a general principle that מירוח Miruach of the הקדש
Hekdesh does not exempt. It counts like in generally he agrees it
exempts and there's something specific about עומר Omer that makes him take
his position. So let's take a look. ועוד, Ve'od, and in addition...
to as a counterproof to the idea that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva.
*Rebbe Akiva* is saying a general principle, אתי *aisi* רב גנא בר
תחליפא *Rav Gana bar Tachlifa* לרב כהנא *le-Rav Kahana*, so רב חנא
בר תחליפא *Rav Chana bar Tachlifa* asked רב כהנא *Rav Kahana* after
the different רב כהנא *Rav Kahana*. Okay, or maybe it's בר מתתיה
*bar Mattasya* and we have to different מר כהנא *Mar Kahana*, רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rebbe Akiva* מחייב mechayev בחלה ובמעשרות *mechayev be-challah u-ve-ma'asrot*,
so here we have a ברייתא braita *braisa* that says the following,
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva's *Rebbe Akiva* says you're חייב chayav *chayav* in
חלה challah *challah* and מעשרות maasros. *ma'asrot*, and this ברייתא braita *braisa*
tells you why you're חייב chayav *chayav* in חלה Challah. *challah* and
מעשר maaser *ma'aser* by the עומר omer. *Omer*, לפי שלא נתנו מעות
אלא לצורך להם *lefi she-lo nitnu ma'os ela le-tzorech lahem*, when they
used money to buy the grain, because as you know we pointed
out the other day, it's not like they owned grain fields, like
that is not a business that the הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* necessarily wanted
to get into, they only needed a certain amount of grain for,
you know, the עומר omer *Omer*, so they went, they found where
there was ripe grain, and they bought it from the owner. So
when they used the money to buy the grain, they were only
using the money, they only sanctified the amount that ultimately was going
to be needed for the flour. They bought more than they needed,
I mean they bought שלוש סאים *shalosh se'im*, but that whole שלוש
סאים *shalosh se'im* did not turn into more than the amount of
flour than they needed, and the intent all along was that the
money would only sanctify the amount that in the end they need
and the amount that in the end they use. So that's רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva. *Rebbe Akiva* saying why you're חייב chayav. *chayav* in
מעשר maaser *ma'aser* and חלה Challah. *challah*, not because הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*
would exempt. הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* would exempt, but the amount that, but
the leftover that gets sold or given, you know, to others was
never הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* in the begin with, it was never sanctified
in the begin with. So תוספות Tosafos *Tosafos* asks, well then why
did the משנה mishnah *Mishnah* say you have to redeem the remainder?
According to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, *Rebbe Akiva* the remainder was never
קדוש kadosh. *kadosh*. The only thing that was קדוש *kadosh* was the
amount that actually was used. So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says, well that
might be true in fact but it looks like it's all קדוש
*kadosh*. I mean הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* is handling all of it. From
people's
perspective, perception, it looks like it's all קדוש *kadosh*, so if you
were to just give this to be eaten freely without it having
to be redeemed, people would think that הקדש hekdesh's *hekdesh* doesn't require
being redeemed.
Where we were saying that הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* buys the whole thing
but only the portion of
that in the end gets used they intended to sanctify. It's a
type of יש ברירה *yesh bereirah*, except יש ברירה *yesh bereirah* is
more like when something happens in the end and retroactively, you know,
we say that was always the way it was. This is more
like you're designating at the outset, but there's an element of יש
ברירה *yesh bereirah*, like you're giving the portfolio, whatever it is, a
hundred dollars, and you're saying right now you're buying all of it,
right well that's actually an interesting question, are you buying all of
it or only sanctify.
But anyway let's get back to the, right, right.
You see part of the question here is
there are two aspects of הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*. הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* is
just a, you know, is a legal entity and can own things.
And also when הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* owns things, things get sanctity. The
objects become sanctified. So normally when we speak about something being קדוש
*kadosh* and being exempt from like תרומות ומעשרות Terumos uMaasros *trumos u-ma'asrot*
and so on, it's not the ownership of הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* that
makes it exempt, it's the fact that the object is a sanctified
object that it remains exempt. That's not always true. For example, sometimes
when you have, let's say, by issues which are really about ownership,
like by נזיקין *nezikin*, בבא קמא *Bava Kamma*, five amudes, it says
שור רעהו ולא שור הקדש hekdesh *shor re'eihu ve-lo shor hekdesh*. If
my ox gores a שור *shor* of הקדש hekdesh's *hekdesh* or a
שור הקדש hekdesh *shor hekdesh* gores my ox, there's no damages that
are paid. So there, it has less to do presumably with the
fact that the ox is sanctified than that the owner is not
a lay person, the owner is הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh*. Okay, so that's
always a question, which is what is the focus when הקדש hekdesh
*hekdesh* is being exempted, is it based on the ownership or the
sanctity of the object. Here, it particularly seems it's about the sanctity
of the object. It seems like because in the end of the
day הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* spent the sixty bucks or whatever it needs
to spend to buy the wheat, they were the owners of the
wheat, so they actually were the owners of it, but presumably what
exempts the wheat, I mean barley, but presumably what exempts the barley,
the grain, from תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-ma'asros, *trumos u-ma'asrot* is not the
fact that it's owned by הקדש hekdesh, *hekdesh* but the fact that
it is קדוש *kadosh*. And what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rebbe Akiva*
is saying here is it might be הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* bought it
and bought all of this grain, but they only intended to make
in terms of what of the object's קדוש *kadosh* only that only
the amount that ultimately was used. And so the part that in
the end turned out was not used might have been owned by
הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh* but not actually קדוש *kadosh*. But that's conceptually what's
happening. It is a little strange because normally the fact that it
becomes קדוש *kadosh* naturally flows from the fact that it's owned by
הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh*. But it seems here that רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva,
*Rebbe Akiva* is saying that they were stipulating not that way. And
it's also interesting that they didn't know what that grain was initially.
It only at the end it turned out that they knew which
was the one they wanted to become קדוש *kadosh* and which was
not. So this is a way to read רבי עקיבא *Rebbe Akiva*'s
position, that it's not a general statement. Generally he agrees that ownership
of הקדש Hekdesh *hekdesh* exempts from מעשרות Maasros *ma'asrot* when it occurs
at the time of מירוח meruach. *meiruach*, or the fact that the
object is קדוש *kadosh* exempts from מעשרות *ma'asrot* and here the issue
is that it was never intended to make the things, to make
the stuff that they weren't going to use קדוש *kadosh*. And as
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* says, therefore the need to redeem was more just
like a ritual for appearance's sake, there really wasn't even a need
to redeem the remainder. Okay, so now we go on.
Yes, the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah* that talked about the whole fanfare about
it that they cut it and with the roasting and that whole
type and all that,
are they talking about this עומר omer? *Omer* that... How does it
get bought and we don't know whether, you know, how does it
end up by the גזבר?
gezbar, Well, oh, yeah, you've, oh, you mean that's true. There was
never a discussion of once they identified the field, that moment of
transaction, of like somebody going to the owner of the field and
actually paying for it. Right. Right. It is about this ritual. Right.
But no, what does happen is, no, it's a public ritual, but
they actually presumably they sent out a messenger of the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, of the of the מקדש Mikdash to do it. Now
it doesn't have to be done by a כהן, kohen, it could
be done by anybody, but presumably it's being done somehow under the
auspices of the מקדש. Mikdash. One imagines, right, somebody's in charge. But
what's what's not discussed in the previous משנה Mishnah was the purchase,
right? Clearly הקדש hekdesh did not own fields, all these fields just
for the sake of עומר. Omer. Oh, maybe they donated it. Right,
that's true. Maybe. Right, you would imagine that. But but in the
end also maybe for the sake of it being communal property and,
you know, there might have been a need to even do some
type of a pro forma purchase, to use communal funds to purchase
it so that it in sort of in a very sort of
formal and objective way is communal property. But yes, I don't imagine
that it was, you know, that people that people were asking a
high price for this. But you're right, that was missing from the
whole discussion was that how they took possession of it.
The מדרש Medrash on רות Rus says that everybody was out in
the fields, they were actually doing the עומר Omer
when רות Rus and נעמי Naomi enter.
And they were all cutting for the sake of the עומר? Omer
Seems like a pretty big... really? I'd have to look at that
מדרש. Medrash. It seems like a pretty big operation just for three
סאה. seah.
It was a happy event. Right.
Right. Definitely. It was a whole major event. That we, yeah. That
we definitely see, yeah. That we definitely see. Okay. So now so
now let's take a look. Now the גמרא Gemara just reiterates this.
Okay. אלא אמר רבי יוחנן, Ela amar Reb Yochanan, so therefore רבי
יוחנן Reb Yochanan said you're right. תלמוד ערוך בפי של רבי עקיבא,
Talmud aruch b'fi shel Rabbi Akiva, it's a established statement, you know,
teaching in the mouth of רבי עקיבא. It's funny because, you know,
רש"י Rashi in other places says it's not like he had a
tradition that רבי עקיבא said that. He sort of is, you know,
is is not
not speculating, but you know, like he sort of reading this based
on his interpretation of רבי עקיבא's position and saying it as if
this is a statement of רבי עקיבא. There's another רש"י Rashi that
does that on the phrase of תלמוד ערוך. Talmud aruch. So anyway,
extrapolating, anyway, that was the word I was looking for. Okay. תלמוד
ערוך בפי של רבי עקיבא, Talmud aruch b'fi shel Rabbi Akiva, it
was a common statement or an established statement in the words in
the mouth of רבי עקיבא, שלא ניתנו מעות אלא לצורך להן. she'lo
nitnu maos ella l'tzorech lahen. The money were always given only for
the end what was needed and the remainder never actually became קדוש.
Okay, very good. So that explains why in principle רבי עקיבא of
course agrees that מירוח הקדש meruach hekdesh exempts and this is a
special case. Now we are going to take a step back and
actually look at this issue: When does ownership of a non- of
הקדש exempt and when does ownership of a non-Jew exempt at different
stages of ownership whether you're talking about מעשר ma'aser, or חלה Challah:
or so on. So the גמרא Gemara uses this as a nice
opportunity to get into more general themes about about
מעשרות. So let's take a look.
Okay. אבל מירוח בעלמא, Aval meruach b'alma, so says the גמרא, Gemara,
that's true in terms of הקדש, there's a special case, אבל מירוח
בעלמא aval meruach b'alma when it comes to general issues about normal
cases about smoothing over the grain, מירוח הקדש בעלמא meruach hekdesh b'alma
when it's הקדש פטור, pater,
that does exempt if you buy it afterwards. מירוח עובדי כוכבים, Meruach
ovdei kochavim, how about the that, because that we said that everybody
agrees, even the חכמים chachamim challenge רבי עקיבא, they said don't you
agree in a normal case that הקדש is owning of it exempts?
So we see everybody agrees that הקדש's owning of the grain exempts
it from מעשר ma'aser when it's at the time of מירוח. meruach.
Now we ask: What about a non-Jew? מירוח עובדי כוכבים תנאי היא,
Meruach ovdei kochavim tana'i hi, but whether when a non-Jew owns it
if that exempts, that is a debate of תנאים Tana'im and we're
going to see in a minute. Let me first explain conceptually how
a non-Jew is different from הקדש and it's in two possible ways.
One, I think, I forget רש"י Rashi or תוספות Tosafot makes this
point, in both cases it's owned by an entity that, you know,
that is not themselves חייב בתרומות ומעשרות. chayav in trumos u'maasros. הקדש
isn't חייב בתרומות ומעשרות, chayav in trumos u'maasros, a non-Jew isn't. It's
obviously not lay-owned. The difference is is that, you know, by הקדש
it goes more fully out of, you know, our control, I mean
it's not just, I don't mean just about the type out of
our sphere, out of our world, becomes something that becomes intrinsically sanctified
and needs to be redeemed, it's not just an issue of ownership,
it's a change of status. That's the point I was pointing about
before, that הקדש is not just an entity that owns things, it
actually create- creates the status change in the object. So in that
way הקדש ownership is a more full exemption or a full change
of status than just ownership of a non-Jew. In that- so that's
one aspect of הקדש which is why we said everybody agrees הקדש's
ownership exempts. The issue about a non-Jew's ownership is a debate. The
other thing, however, about a non-Jew, which could make it easier for
the fact that if it's a non-Jew who's ju... doing it to
become exempt, is just another discussion in that same גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
in גיטין *Gittin*, which is completely absent, thank you, which is completely
absent here, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* and תוספות *Tosafot* both mention it, which
is whether יש קניין לעובד כוכבים להפקיע מיד תרומות ומעשרות trumos u-ma'asros,
*yesh kinyan l'oveid kochavim l'hafkiyah miyad trumot u'maasrot*, whether a non-Jew's ownership
of the land of Israel means that it is no longer, you
know, because it's no longer under Jewish control, does that mean that
to some degree the land loses קדושה kedusha, *kedusha*?
And not what? No, that's not, so I want to make clear.
Okay. Now, it doesn't mean it fully loses קדושה *kedusha*, but it
means at least enough that it would not make the grain that
grows from it obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros. *trumot u'maasrot*. So
that's always a factor. Oh, you're bringing a non-Jew into it, we
have to decide maybe the fact that he owns it means that
you're not חייב chayav. *chayav* in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros *trumot u'maasrot*.
That by the way is the whole basis for the היתר מכירה
hetter mechira, *hetter mechira*, right? That if a non-Jew owns it, then
the status of the agricultural laws that apply to the land don't
apply if it's owned by a non-Jew. So that is ignored here.
The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* basically assumes that we're going to sort of
take for argument's sake an assumption that non-Jewish ownership of the land,
it still is obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros *trumot u'maasrot*. So
any exemption that we're going to see here is going to be
based on the principle that it's not because of the ownership of
the land, but it's because the stage of the processing was done
by a non-Jew. And that's what we're focused on, the מירוח meruach
*miruach*, the smoothing out, that stage of the processing, that was done
by a non-Jew, that's our question. Now it's important because regardless owned
by a Jew or a non-Jew. Now it's important because to appreciate
that these are different issues. If you say that the fact that
the land was owned by the non-Jew is enough to exempt it,
then if I buy the standing grain from the non-Jew and I
take it and I thresh it and I whatever do the מירוח
meruach *miruach*, it doesn't matter, it's still exempt, because it grew from
land owned by a non-Jew and therefore it does not have קדושה
*kedusha* of the grain and not חייב chayav *chayav* in תרומות ומעשרות
trumos u'ma'asros. *trumot u'maasrot*. If you assume ownership of the land of
a non-Jew has that effect. However, let's take a flip case. I,
the Jew, grew the grain. I sold this—not with non-Jewish workers now.
Let's bracket the worker case, that's a little more complicated. Let's talk
about ownership of the grain as opposed to ownership of the land.
So I grew the grain, and I now of course I want
to get out of תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros, *trumot u'maasrot*. We're going
to see this in a minute. So I go to my friend,
the non-Jew, and I say, hey, make a deal, I'll sell you
all my grain, you'll do the מירוח meruach *miruach*, you'll—I'll buy it
back from you, I'll give you a nice little percentage, great, he
does that, I don't have to pay תרומות ומעשרות terumos and ma'asros.
*trumot u'maasrot*. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to in a minute
deal with how do we close up that loophole. Okay, but that's
the issue of מירוח meiruach, עובדי כוכבים *miruach ovdei kochavim*, מירוח meiruach,
נכרי nochri *miruach nochri*, which is, it's totally my grain, it's totally
חייב chayav *chayav* in תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot, *trumot u'maasrot* or it
was until I sold it to him, and it's not that it
didn't grow from the right land, but it's that he did that
act and it was under his ownership when it had a מירוח
meroach *miruach* and that is enough to exempt it. So our question
is about that, is about the moment of the processing of מירוח
meroach *miruach*. For now we're going to bracket the workers' case, like
what if it's my grain, my thing, no. And we're going to
bracket that, we're going to deal with—we're going to assume he owned
it at that time and then I bought it back, but there
we're going to assume that the grain is חייב chayav, *chayav* and
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* for argument's sake or whatever for simplicity's sake
is not getting into the question of ownership of the non-Jew of
the land. For now we're going to assume either it's a Jew's
grain that they sold to a non-Jew, or yes it was the
non-Jew's grain but we'll assume for argument's sake that that does not
exempt the land from תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot *trumot u'maasrot* and the
only question is the moment of מירוח meroach *miruach*. Okay, so now
let's take a look. On the one hand, again, to repeat, on
the one hand, let's not deal with that, on the one hand
הקדש *Hekdesh* therefore is more obvious that הקדש *Hekdesh*'s מירוח mi'ruach, *miruach*
exempts, because הקדש *Hekdesh*'s ownership of the grain totally takes, you know,
more fundamentally changes the status of the grain. And the issue of
the non-Jew is less obvious if you bracket the question of the
non-Jew's ownership of the land. Let's not get to the issue of
partnership. Okay, so let's take a look. So מירוח mi'ruach עובדי כוכבים
תנאי היא *miruach ovdei kochavim tannai hi*. If a non-Jew does the
מירוח mi'ruach *miruach*, that is a debate of תנאים Tannaim, *Tannaim*. Where
do we see this? דתניא *D'tanya*, it's taught in a ברייתא Braitah
*Baraisa*: תורמין משל ישראל על של ישראל *tormin mishel Yisrael al shel
Yisrael*, ומשל עובדי כוכבים על של עובדי כוכבים *u'mishel ovdei kochavim al
shel ovdei kochavim*, ומשל כותים Kutim על של כותים Kutim *u'mishel Kutim
al shel Kutim*, ומשל כל על של כל *u'mishel kol al shel
kol*. Now here's—so far there was no big חידוש *chiddush* there because
everything is all the same status. Here's the חידוש *chiddush*: ומשל כל
על של כל דברי רבי מאיר divrei Rabbi Meir. *u'mishel kol al
shel kol divrei Rabbi Meir*. From any type of grain on any
other type of grain. So I can be מפריש mafresh, *mafrish* on
my grain that was grown in Jewish land and processed by Jews
and is completely obligated in תרומות ומעשרות terumot u'ma'asrot *trumot u'maasrot*, and
I have this other grain that was grown on non-Jewish land in
Israel and processed by non-Jews, and I can be מפריש *mafrish* my
תרומות trumos. ומעשרות *trumot u'maasrot* from the non-Jewish grain and exempt my
Jewish grain. Because the חידוש *chiddush* is is that there is no
different obligation, which that's not obvious. There's no different obligation of the
grain grown by the non-Jew. does not exempt. Okay, and the ownership
of the non-Jew of the land also does not exempt. That's what
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says. רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, דברי מאיר ורבי
יהודה. divrei Meir v'Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, that's what רבי
מאיר Rebbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda say. רבי יוסי ורבי
שמעון אומרים, Rebbi Yosi v'Rebbi Shimon omrim, רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rebbi
Yosi v'Rebbi Shimon say, תורמין משל ישראל על של ישראל ומשל עובדי
כוכבים על של כותים. tormin mishel Yisrael al shel Yisrael umishel ovdei
kochavim al shel Kutim. Here's where you can crossover the lines. Obviously
Jew on Jew, yes. Non-Jew on Samaritans, yes. ומשל כותים על של
עובדי כוכבים, umishel Kutim al shel ovdei kochavim, Samaritans on non-Jews, yes.
אבל לא משל ישראל על של עובדי כוכבים ומשל כותים, aval lo
mishel Yisrael al shel ovdei kochavim umishel Kutim, but you cannot take
תרומה Terumah from Jewish grain on non-Jewish grain or Samaritans' grain because
that would be from grain that's obligated on grain that is biblically
exempt. ולא משל עובדי כוכבים ולא משל כותים על של ישראל, velo
mishel ovdei kochavim velo mishel Kutim al shel Yisrael, and not from
grain grown by Samaritans and non-Jews you cannot take from that תרומות
trumos. ומעשרות to exempt grain grown by Jews, because the grain grown
by Jews is biblically obligated, this other stuff is only rabbinic, and
you cannot take from obligated to non-obligated. It's interesting parenthetically that they
put the כותים in the same category as non-Jews. It's a basically
standing question in the גמרא Gemara whether כותים have the status of
Jews or non-Jews and the Torah tells the story in the time
of the first בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash after it was destroyed, that
they put in that the Samaritans came to the land, they were
placed there by what's-his-name, נבוכדנצר, Nevuchadnezzar, and then they started adopting the
practice, first they started worshipping עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, then God sent
lions, and then they asked, why's God sending lions? We're just doing
what we used to do. Oh well, the God of this land
needs you to worship Him. Anyway then they started becoming worshipping the
God of the land, and obviously the Samaritans were a whole sort
of history in the second temple period. So there was always this
question, did they really convert or not really convert? This passage at
least sounds like they didn't. It's treating their grain the exact same
status as the non-Jew's grain. תוספות tries to figure out how does
that work with other passages where the general assumption in the גמרא
Gemara is usually that they are like Jews. Anyway that's a parenthetic
point. What you see here is is that here's the debate: according
to רבי מאיר Reb Meir and רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, grain grown
by non-Jews is fully obligated even though presumably it was in their
land and they did the מירוח. mi'ruach So presumably it assumes two
things: A, their ownership of the land doesn't exempt, and B, the
מירוח mi'ruach doesn't exempt. And the other opinion say, no, it is
exempt, and at least for now the גמרא Gemara. is focusing not
on the land issue, but the מירוח meruach. would be enough to
exempt it. So that is a debate of תנאים, Tannaim the status
of מירוח meruach done by a non-Jew. Now we move from מעשרות
to the other thing mentioned in the משנה Mishnah which is חלה.
challah, So now we're on the official beginning of today's דף סז
עמוד א daf samech-zayin amud aleph at the bottom.
Okay, so גלגול הקדש פוטר.
gilgul hekdesh poter.
What הקדש does
the גלגול,
gilgul, which is
basically the like what do
you call
it,
what's this when you do
with the
dough? The rolling. That's what
it's called, the rolling. Okay
anyway, when they do the kneading and the rolling,
that's
the moment that you're חייב
chayav.
in חלה. challah, So when הקדש does
it, you're exempt. Now that's
implicit. Now actually it's
not in
the משנה Mishnah
because our
משנה Mishnah wasn't dealing with
a case when הקדש did it. Our משנה
Mishnah.
was dealing that you bought it before it had the kneading and
the rolling. דתנן, detnan, you taught in the משנה Mishnah in חלה:
challah? הקדיש עיסתה עד שלא גלגלה, hikdish issatah ad shelo gilgelah, it's
very explicit in this משנה. Mishnah Somebody sanctifies their dough before this
time of the sort of kneading and rolling, ופדאה, ufada'ah, and then
he redeemed it, חייבת. chayaves. So you're חייב chayav. because the dough
is obligated because you redeemed it. You sanctified it and redeemed it,
and nothing happened between those two moments. You sanctified it before you
did the rolling and kneading, and you redeemed it before you did
the kneading and the rolling. So obviously it goes back to being
חייב. chayav
חייבת. chayaves. משגלגלה ופדאה חייבת. mishegilgelah ufada'ah chayaves. So how about the
other flip side is you did the kneading, one minute, am I
reading this right? Hold on. I got to put the, I'm putting
the גמרא Gemara here, minute. הקדיש עיסתה עד שלא גלגלה ופדאה חייבת
משגלגלה ופדאה חייבת. hikdish issatah ad shelo gilgelah ufada'ah chayaves mishegilgelah ufada'ah
chayaves.
Right,
I mean it means that the הקדש also came after that moment.
So the first case is you sanctified it and redeemed it before
גלגול. gilgul. The second case is you sanctified it and redeemed it
after גלגול. gilgul. It's also חייבת. chayaves. Okay, so if you did
both the sanctifying and the redeeming either before גלגול gilgul or after
גלגול gilgul and the moment of גלגול gilgul you owned it and
you were doing the kneading and the rolling, then obviously it's going
to be חייב. chayav, Now we get to the more interesting case.
הקדיש עד שלא גלגלו. hikdish ad shelo gilgelu. You sanctified it before
the rolling and the kneading. וגלגלו הגזבר, vegilgelo hagezbar, and then the
גזבר, the person in charge of the temple treasury, הקדש, took it
over and they did the kneading and the rolling. ואחר כך פדאה,
ve'achar kach fada'ah, and then you redeemed it. So the moment of
the rolling it was owned by the הקדש. That's the key moment.
Then פטורה, pturah, then it's exempt. שבשעת חובתה היתה פטורה, shebishas chovasah
hayesa pturah, that at the moment of obligation, the moment of גלגול
gilgul when it becomes dough, then it was exempt, it was owned
by הקדש. Okay, so very clear. If הקדש owns it at the
key moment, whether by grain, by מעשר, ma'aser the key moment is
the מירוח, the smoothing. By חלה, challah. the key moment is the
kneading and the rolling and the making of dough. If הקדש owns
at the key moment, that חייב—I chayav, mean excuse me, that exempts
even if you buy it afterwards. And if a non-Jew owns at
the moment of מירוח, that's a debate. So the one part of
the box we haven't filled in is what's the story of the
non-Jew in the case of חלה, challah, in the case of גלגול,
gilgul, and that's what now we're going to try to figure out.
So בעי רבא. baei Rava. So רבא Rava asked: גלגול עובד כוכבים
מאי? Gilgul oveid kochavim mai? What's the story of the non-Jew who
owned it at the time of גלגול, gilgul, that's the time of
the rolling of the dough? מתניתין, Mitnenan, we caught in the משנה
Mishnah the following: גר שנתגייר והיתה לו עיסה. Ger she-nitgayer v'hayta lo
issa. So we actually had the interesting case yesterday that was being
raised about somebody that converts during the ספירה. sefira. What is their
obligation in terms of counting the remainder of the ספירה? sefira? Well
here we have a case about somebody that was making dough when
they were Jewish—they left their dough made when they were not Jewish,
they left their dough to go to the מקוה mikvah to become
a גר, ger, and then they came back to finish their dough.
So is it חייב chayav or exempt in חלה? challah. Okay, so
let's take a look. גר שנתגייר, Ger she-nitgayer, so a person converted.
והיתה לו עיסה, V'hayta lo issa, and he had dough in his
house. נעשית עד שלא נתגייר, Na'aseit ad she-lo nitgayer, if he made
the dough before he converted, פטור, patur, he's exempt.
משנתגייר, Mi-she-nitgayer, if he made it after he converted, meaning that's when
he let's say, you know, rolled it and added the water and
the flour, חייב, chayav then it's חייב. chayav ספק, Safek, if it's
he doesn't—if it's unclear, he forgets exactly when he made the dough,
חייב. chayav. So you're strict and you say it's חייב chayav in
חלה. challah, So this basically assumes that if a non-Jew owned it
at the time of it becoming dough, of the rolling and the
kneading, it's exempt, right? The whole question is you have to determine
when did it become dough, but if he owned it at that
time it would be exempt.
It didn't say גלגול, gilgul, it said עיסה. issa.
נעשית עיסה, Na'aseit issa, yeah that is interesting that it uses a
different phrase of נעשית עיסה na'aseit issa and it didn't use the
more specific phrase of גלגול. gilgul. גמרא Gemara assumes it's the same.
Yeah, I don't know why, does anybody know, does—maybe I zoned out
before—but גלגול gilgul translated by Artscroll was kneading, not kneading, the
rolling, the rolling.
Yeah, that's a good
question.
Kneading and kneading are the same. When you knead...
well it depends, like if you're making a batter versus...
if you're making a batter versus לישה, lisha, I thought לישה lisha
was kneading.
Water and flour, that's true. It's a good question. And then you—and
putting it...
so
you're saying then it also fits better with the word of נעשית
עיסה? na'aseit issa? Okay, that's a good point.
Anyway, okay, so the question here was raised about what exactly means—what
exactly the moment was. I'll read you the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם
Rambam in ח' ב' Chet-Bet in הלכות ביכורים, Hilchos Bikkurim, that's where
he puts חלה, challah? says the following: אין היחיד מפרישין חלה כשייתן
המים ויתערב הקמח במים מפרישין חלה מתחילת דבר שנילוש. Ein hayach mafreishin
challah keshe-yiten hamayim v'yitarev hakemach b'mayim mafreshin challah mi-tchilat davar she-nilo.
So as soon as you add the water and mix it, שנאמר
ראשית עריסותיכם. she-ne'emar reishit arisoteichem. But the ראב"ד Ra'avad there says, אמר
אברהם אין יעשה לעשות כן, amar Avraham ein ya'aseh la'asot kein, you
shouldn't take it immediately after you add the water, אלא אם כן
עשה בה רבכיים ראשית עריסותיכם שנחשבת עיסה. ella im kein asa b'ha
reiveki'im reishit arisoteichem she-nichshevet issa.
But he says, ראב"ד Ra'avad says, okay, technically it will work at
that moment, but that's not ideal, and it sounds like it's ideal
to make it after you've actually, you know, kneaded it and made
it more into dough. But the רמב"ם—but Rambam anyway, so the רמב"ם—but
Rambam the key here is not when you actually are מפריש, the
key here actually is when is the moment of חיוב? chiyuv? And
the ראב"ד Ra'avad and the רמב"ם Rambam do agree that the moment
of חיוב chiyuv is the adding of the water. It's actually מפורש
משנת חלה, meforash mishnat challah, so just shows... חלה. challah Okay, so
I stand corrected. Okay, so here it does mean—I have to see
actually what the word גלגול gilgul actually means, because it could be—but
anyway, okay, we'll bracket that. It is clear at least that—that the
חיוב chiyuv does come as soon as the water is added and,
you know, at least it's mixed together. It might not be kneaded,
but it's mixed together to create some form of dough. So that
it does work better with the phrase of נעשית עיסה. na'aseit issa.
Okay, so what do you see? You see that ownership of a
non-Jew according to this ברייתא Braitah does exempt. So if ownership of
a non-Jew exempts, what's the question? Is that a consensus, or is
that only according to the opinion that said that ownership of—that ownership
also exempted for the case of what do you call it, for
the case of not just חלה, challah but for the case of
מעשר ma'aser? as well? So is it the same opinion or is
this a consensus when it comes to חלה? Challah And if it
is a consensus, why would חלה Challah. be different? So let's take
a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
הא
מן קתני לה? Ha man katani lah? Who is—who is the author
of this ברייתא Braitah that by—when—with when a נכרי owns the gra—owns
the wheat at the time of it becoming dough that it's exempt?
היא והכל היא? Hee ve-hakol hee? Is it everybody's opinion? ואפילו רבי
מאיר ורבי יהודה דקמחייב התם, Ve-afilu Rabi Meir ve-Rabi Yehuda de-kam-chayiv hatam,
even Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda that say over there by מעשר
ma'aser. that the ownership does not exempt and that you're חייב, chayav.
פטרי הכא? patrei hacha? Here they would exempt? Why? Why should you—why
should it be more of an exemption here by חלה Challah. than
by מעשר? ma'aser? So it does not give any sort of conceptual
reason, it gives a technical one based on the verse. התם הוא
דכתיב דגנך דגנך. Hatam hu di-chtiv dgancha dgancha. יתירה *yeteira* הוי מיעוט
אחר מיעוט הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות *havei mi'ut achar mi'ut
havei mi'ut achar mi'ut ela lerabbos*. There it says the word דגנך
*degancha* a couple of times when it speaks about taking תרומות terumot,
ומעשרות *trumot u-ma'asros* it says רש״י *Rashi* quotes the
פסוקים *psukim*, what are the פסוקים *psukim*? לא תוכל לאכל בשעריך מעשר
ma'aser, דגנך *Lo tuchal leechol bish'arecha ma'asar degancha*, ואכלת לפני ה' אלהיך
מעשר ma'aser, דגנך *ve-achalta lifnei Hashem Elokecha ma'asar degancha*, ראשית דגנך *reishis
degancha*. There's a lot of דגנך *deganchas*. So one of the דגנך
*deganchas* exempts הקדש *hekdesh*'s grain, grain from מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser*. One exempts
non-Jews. But then there's another דגנך *degancha*. So of course in the
classic Talmudic way, oh, we have another מיעוט *mi'ut*, we have another
limitation, it's obviously coming to include, not to exclude. Okay, so because
there's an extra דגנך *degancha*, that's where רבי מאיר Reb Meir *Rebbe
Meir* and רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda, *Rebbe Yehuda* would include in the
case of מעשר ma'aser *ma'aser*. הוי מיעוט אחר מיעוט אלא לרבות *Havei
mi'ut achar mi'ut ela lerabbos*,
so coming to include even non-Jews.
That's how they get to include non-Jews by the מעשר ma'aser, *ma'aser*.
How do you
know it doesn't include הקדש *hekdesh*? אבל *Aval* so that's what תוספות
*Tosfos* says. תוספות *Tosfos* says why do we pick non-Jews over הקדש
*hekdesh*? And he says the reason I told you before, that הקדש
*hekdesh* is the first thing you're going to exclude because it affects
not only ownership but the status of the grain. So the most
obvious thing to exclude is הקדש *hekdesh*, and that's why in all
these cases הקדש *hekdesh* clearly exempts and the question was whether the
non-Jewish ownership exempts. So there we can have a debate, it's an
extra דגנך *degancha*, maybe we include non-Jews. אבל הכא *Aval hacha*, here,
תרי עריסותיכם כתיב *trei arisoseichem ktiv*. It doesn't say three times, it
only says twice. And twice we already we know what to do
with it. Now here there's a question about the גרסא *girsa*. I
know what, here's a question of the גרסא *girsa*, so I'll read
it with the amended גרסא *girsa*. חד עריסותיכם *Chad arisoseichem*, if you
skip, I'm going down a line, I'm going to skip down, חד
עריסותיכם דלא עיסה של עובדי כוכבים *chad arisoseichem d'lo isa shel ovdei
kochavim*, not non-Jews, וחד עריסותיכם *ve-chad arisoseichem* they stick in the words
דלא עיסה של הקדש *d'lo isa shel hekdesh*. Okay, so you have
two, meaning there's a re-read of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* because רש״י
*Rashi* really re-reads it. He says it really says דגנך *degancha* three
times. The real question is do you need a פסוק *pasuk* to
exclude הקדש *hekdesh*? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* here is not really discussing
how you know to exclude הקדש *hekdesh*. So the way רש״י *Rashi*
reads this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is it says דגנך *degancha* three times,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* only mentions two, one to get out of
הקדש *hekdesh* and the other two is a מיעוט אחר מיעוט *mi'ut
achar mi'ut* and that winds up including. Here by עריסותיכם *arisoseichem*, which
is by חלה Challah *challah*, which is by לעריסותיכם *l'arisoseichem* for us,
it only says it twice, so one is הקדש *hekdesh*, one is
non-Jew and you don't have a third one to include non-Jews. You
have a second one to exclude non-Jews. That's the way רש״י *Rashi*
reads it. The other way, this is תוספות *Tosfos* asks as a
general question, do you normally assume you need two פסוקים *psukim* to
include to exclude non-Jews and הקדש *hekdesh* or does one assume to
exclude? So the other way to read this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
like more פשט *pshat* of what we have in front of us,
that if you have two דגנך *deganchas*, the third one is written
somewhere else and for some reason it's not going to bother us.
You only have two, one excludes both non-Jews and הקדש *hekdesh*, both.
The second one comes to include, so it would, you know, because
it's a double מיעוט *mi'ut* so that limits what's excluded, only הקדש
*hekdesh* is excluded not non-Jews. That's two. Here yes it does say
two, but because it says two, it's not coming to be more
inclusive, it's coming for two because one עריסותיכם *arisoseichem* is not needed
to include or exclude, one עריסותיכם *arisoseichem* comes to tell you how
much flour do you need to be חייב chayav. *chayav* in חלה
Challah *challah* and that fits better our printed גרסא *girsa*. So if
you look back at our printed גרסא *girsa* it goes like this:
כתיב חד עריסותיכם *ktiv chad arisoseichem* by the little ב *beis* in
brackets, כדי עיסתכם *kedei isaschem* to mean how much flour, the same
amount of dough that you used in the מדבר *midbar*, about the
עשרון isaron *isaron* flour, you know, that when you made you had
an עשרון *isaron* of flour, we're not going to go into the
exact computation, but that tells the שיעור shiur *shiur* of dough, the
quantity that's חייב chayav *chayav* in חלה Challah *challah*. וחד עריסותיכם *ve-chad
arisoseichem* and the other דלא עיסה של עובדי כוכבים ולא עיסה של
הקדש *d'lo isa shel ovdei kochavim ve-lo isa shel hekdesh*, which excludes
both non-Jews and הקדש *hekdesh* equally. So this read of the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*, you don't have a separate פסוק *pasuk* for הקדש *hekdesh*
and non-Jews. One word excludes both non-Jews and הקדש *hekdesh*. So how
does it work? It worked by מעשר *ma'aser*, one thing excluded both,
the extra word then came to include, so non-Jews were included. Here
you have two פסוקים *psukim*, but you but two words, but they're
not both operating in this inclusion-exclusion. One word is operating to tell
you the amount and the other word is just excluding, so it
excludes equally non-Jews or equal opportunity, you know, excluder, so you know
we exclude equally the non-Jews and the הקדש *hekdesh*. We do that
with the one word and therefore you don't have another פסוק *pasuk*
to come back and include the non-Jews. So however the technical computations
work out, it's saying look, maybe even רבי מאיר Reb Meir *Rebbe
Meir* and רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* there because of the
פסוקים *psukim* include non-Jews, say non-Jews' grain is חייב chayav, *chayav* in
מעשר *ma'aser*, would still say that it is exempt in חלה Challah.
*challah* and this statement that when the non-Jew owns it it's exempt
in חלה Challah, *challah* is according to everybody, is a consensus. That's
one possibility. או דלמא *Od deilma* or do we say רבי יוסי
ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yose ve'Rabbi Shimon, תני לה *Rebbe Yosi ve-Rebbe Shimon
tani lah*, this ברייתא Braitah *beraisa*, this משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* excuse me,
that says that the dough of a non-Jew is exempt in חלה
Challah, *challah*, that's only רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yose ve'Rabbi Shimon,
*Rebbe Yosi ve-Rebbe Shimon* דקא פטרי *d'ka patrei* that they exempt by
also by the מעשר *ma'aser* case. אבל רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה *Aval
Rebbe Meir ve-Rebbe Yehuda*, but רבי מאיר *Rebbe Meir* and רבי יהודה
Reb Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* that a non-Jew's grain is obligated in מעשר
*ma'aser*, גמירי ראשית ראשית מהתם *gemiri reishis reishis me-hasam*, they make a
גזירה gezeira שוה *gezeira shava*, it says ראשית עריסותיכם *reishis arisoseichem* and
it says ראשית *reishis* by תרומה trumah. *trumah*, so they make a
גזירה gezeira שוה *gezeira shava*. would be consistent and there would not
be consensus here. So רבא Rava did not know the answer to
this, whether the debate really still applies in the case of חלה
Challah. as well. So אמר רבא, amar Rava, so רבא Rava said
after he posed this question, יהי רעוא דאחזייה בחלמא, yehei Ra'ava d'achzayei
b'chulma, it should be God's will that I should have a vision
in a dream or that I should see them maybe, רבי מאיר
and רבי יהודה, but anyway I should see in a dream what
the answer to this question is, you know, about whether the debate
applies here as well in חלה. Challah. So הדר אמר רבא, hadar
amar Rava, then רבא Rava came a few days later, maybe had
his dream, and אמר amar and he said, what? Or he figured
it out on his own but he actually but he then came
and he doesn't have any more evidence and he later then said,
מן דאמר מירוח עובדי כוכבים פוטר גלגול עובדי כוכבים פוטר. man d'amar
meroach ovdei kochavim poter gilgul ovdei kochavim poter. It's a consistent debate.
If you say that the non-Jew's ownership of מירוח of the smoothing
over the pile exempts from תרומות ומעשרות, it will also exempt from
חלה. Challah. Well that was never questioned. But now it's the other
part. מן דאמר מירוח עובדי כוכבים אינו פוטר, man d'amar meroach ovdei
kochavim eino poter, רבי מאיר and רבי יהודה that say the מירוח
of a non-Jew does not exempt from תרומות ומעשרות, they would also
argue by the חלה Challah case as well they would say גלגול
עובדי כוכבים אינו פוטר, gilgul ovdei kochavim eino poter, when the non-Jew
makes the dough it also does not exempt. Okay, so רבא Rava
said I don't really know whether the debate is consistent or not,
and but in the end he came back and he said you
know it to me it makes sense, I don't know if he
had his vision in a dream or not, but to me it
makes sense that it is the same debate and therefore although we
don't have a recorded opinion of תנאים that say that if a
non-Jew owns the חלה Challah. it's חייב, chayav he's going to assume
that רבי מאיר and רבי יהודה would say yes, even if the
non-Jew owned the חלה Challah, at the time when it became into
dough, it would still be חלה. Challah, A very interesting גמרא. Gemara
Well רב פפא Rav Pappa is not going to accept it. Okay,
איתיביה eiseiveih רב פפא Rav Pappa לרבא. l'Rava. So רב פפא Rav
Pappa asked רבא Rava because he says I'm going to prove to
you that everybody agrees by חלה, Challah okay let's take a look,
that it's exempt. Oh here we have the following תוספתא. Tosefta. עובד
כוכבים
שהפריש פטר חמור וחלה, Oveid kochavim she-hifrishi peter chamor v'challah, a non-Jew
separated out a פטר חמור, peter chamor, the firstborn of a donkey,
right? רש"י Rashi says it might mean the sheep that replaces the
donkey, תוספות says it means the donkey itself, but either way, and
חלה, Challah he separates out חלה. Challah מודיעין אותו שהוא פטור, modi'in
oso she-hu patur,
you tell him you know what this is not really you know
you really weren't obligated and this stuff really doesn't have the status
of פטר חמור peter chamor and it doesn't really have the status
of חלה. Challah. Now why that should exactly matter is not clear,
I mean he is a non-Jew and he's not bound by these
laws, but it could be in case let's say a Jew buys
it, so the Jew should know that it's not really have the
status, or maybe if he converts, רש"י Rashi indicates that maybe that's
the relevance of that, but the point is it's very nice that
he did this but it does not really get that status. So
here again you see that the author of this ברייתא Braitah, assumes
that the non-Jew when he owns the flour does not become חייב
chayav in חלה. Challah Okay that's clear. Okay. וחלה נאכלת לזרים, v'chalaso
ne'echeles l'zarim,
and the חלה Challah. has no status of הקדש to be eaten
by non-כהנים Kohanim because it was never חייב chayav in חלה. Challah
ופטר חמור גוזז ועובד בו, u-peter chamor gozez v'oveid bo, and the
firstborn donkey does not have limit of holiness, right רש"י Rashi assumes
it was a sheep, right you do not do too much shearing
of your donkeys, okay so anyway so presumably it's the sheep that
was to exchange it, you're not limited how you can use it
and you can shear it and work it. Okay. So now it
says הא, ha, so that's about the חלה, Challah, so he's saying
now it's curious so when is the ברייתא from what? I don't
remember it's a good question. So it's curious that the ברייתא only
mentions חלה, Challah it doesn't mention the more sort of first case
right to get חלה Challah you need to have grain and let
it mention תרומה. trumah So it is a little bit of an
argument from silence which is always a little weak but he's going
to try to infer the fact that תרומה trumah wasn't mentioned. חלה
Challah is פטור, patur, so that implies חלה Challah, is פטור patur
but תרומה trumah. would actually have the status of תרומה. trumah הא,
ha, so says רב פפא, Rav Pappa, that suggests תרומתו אסורה, trumaso
asurah, that the תרומה trumah. would be אסור asur if a non-Jew
took תרומה. trumah והאי תנא דאמר מירוח עובדי כוכבים אינו פוטר, v'hai
tanna d'amar meroach ovdei kochavim eino poter,
so here's a תנא tanna that implicitly is saying that the non-Jew's
מירוח of the smoothing out does not פוטר poter from תרומה trumah
and implicitly saying the non-Jew's תרומה trumah. does have the status as
תרומה. trumah וגלגול עובדי כוכבים פוטר, v'gilgul ovdei kochavim poter,
but the non-Jew's making a flour does exempt from חלה. Challah So
you see this ברייתא sounds like it's saying that the non-Jew's ownership
exempts from חלה Challah, but still remains obligated in תרומות. So there
you have exactly splitting the vote, חייב chayav in תרומה trumah... but
פטור patur in חלה. Challah? ועוד איתיביה רבינא לרבא, v'od eiseiveih Ravina
l'Rava,
and רבינא Ravina asked for רבא Rava, more than an argument from
silence, actually an explicit statement. To get another ברייתא, right exactly. So
let's take a look what he said, חלת עובדי כוכבים בארץ ותרומתו
בחוצה לה, challas ovdei kochavim ba-aretz v'trumaso b'chutz lah, maybe that's the
problem, tells you rather than relying on dreams you should have done
a little more research.
Okay so חלת עובדי כוכבים בארץ ותרומתו בחוצה לה, challas ovdei kochavim
ba-aretz v'trumaso b'chutz lah,
here's another explicit statement about the status of things owned by a
non-Jew. A non-Jew takes חלה Challah? from grain grown in the land
or he takes
תרומה... trumah But anyway, in the lands immediately surrounding Israel, okay? In
the lands like in Syria, right, and even though there's a question
that Syria might have had some קדושה, so even if it didn't,
at least רבננא, rabanana, in the lands immediately surrounding Israel, they extended
a רבנן rabanan obligation of תרומות ומעשרות. So here it says if
a non-Jew makes חלה, challah? makes dough in grain grown in the
land, nevertheless it's fully פטור. patur. Or if
he for תרומות ומעשרות of grain grown outside of the land, it's
fully פטור. patur. But obviously the suggestion is that תרומות ומעשרות of
grain grown in the land would be חייב. chayav. I mean you're
circling around that one case. So חלת עובדי כוכבים בארץ Challas ovdei
kochavim ba'aretz or חלה challah? for flour grain grown in the land,
ותרומתו בחוץ לארץ, u'trumaso be'chutz la'aretz, or תרומה trumah that was grown
out of for grain grown out of land, מודינו שהוא פטור. modinu
shehu patur. You tell him it's really exempt from any obligation, it
doesn't have the status, חלתו נאכלת לזרים, challaso ne'echeles le'zarim, the חלה
challah can be eaten by
non-כהנים, Kohanim, ותרומתו אינה מדמאה, u'trumaso einah medama'ah, and the תרומה trumah
does not cause דימוע, dimua, meaning that if תרומה trumah gets mixed
up with חולין, chullin, you have to treat the entire mixture as
if it's תרומה trumah and it cannot be eaten by non-כהנים. Kohanim.
That would not be true in this case of the תרומה trumah
taken from grain grown out of the land. So again, this is
another argument for טעמא, ta'ama, but this is a stronger argument because
it's talking about תרומה trumah and it only exempts the תרומה trumah
grown outside of Israel. So it's very clear the תרומה trumah. grown
in Israel, grain grown in Israel, even by a non-Jew would be
חייב in תרומה. trumah הא תרומתו בארץ, ha trumaso ba'aretz, the תרומה
trumah, of grain grown in Israel, אסורה asura is forbidden, has a
real status of תרומה, trumah ומדמאה, u'medama'ah, and causes דימוע dimua if
it's mixed up with חולין chullin grain. והאי תנא דאמר מירוח עובד
כוכבים אינו פוטר, ve'hai tanna de'amar mi'ruach oved kochavim eino poter, so
here you see clearly this תנא tanna holds that a non-Jew's, you
know, doing the מירוח, the smoothing, does not exempt. Again it's clear
that his תרומה trumah would be חייב. Nevertheless גלגול עובדי כוכבים פוטר,
gilgul ovdei kochavim poter, his doing making the dough does exempt, his
חלה challah is exempt but his תרומה trumah is חייב. So that
is actually two very clear ברייתות braisos and the second one even
clearer than the first, that there's a somebody who holds that a
non-Jew can be חייב in תרומה trumah but exempt in חלה, the
grain. So there you see that the vote is split. So רבא,
Rava why are you saying that the, you know, that everybody is
consistent? Here you see חלה where more we more exempt than by
תרומות ומעשרות. So the גמרא Gemara says, מדרבנן, miderabbanan, alright, you've proven
to me that there's a split there, but that is not a
דאורייתא de'oraisa position. That the author of those משניות mishnayos really holds
that, you know, as they're really the people here who was it,
רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון, Rabbi Yose ve'Rabbi Shimon, that says non-Jewish ownership
exempts. And they would say it exempts by חלה, that you see,
and they should say it equally exempts by תרומות. So why do
those ברייתות braisos not say that it exempts by תרומה terumah if
they should have? That's a רבנן rabbanan issue. Now what is the
רבנן rabbanan issue? We said before, גזירה משום בעלי כיסין, gezeira mishum
ba'alei kisin, the concern of wealthy people, בעלי כיסין, ba'alei kisin, literally
people of pocket, okay, which means people that have a lot of
grain and have a big profit to make and maybe they're less
about their own, you know, family farm than they are about mega
business. And they do not want to be giving
ten percent of תרומות ומעשרות, so maybe twenty percent if there's two
מעשר. So we're afraid that they're going to take all their grain,
sell it to a non-Jew, have him do the מירוח and buy
it back. Now according to רבי יוסי ורבי שמעון, they could do
that because מירוח of a non-Jew exempts. So in order to close
that loophole, we're going to say מירוח of a non-Jew does not
exempt. So רבא is saying, yes you're right, but really that's רבי
יוסי ורבי שמעון, and even though they say it על פי דין
al pi din according to the Torah it exempts, in practice they're
saying the מירוח of a non-Jew does not exempt so people do
not use that loophole. Okay, that makes a lot of sense that
that would be a loophole you would want to close.
Okay, what about the bakery,
like with dough?
So the גמרא Gemara is going to say why don't you worry
about using the same loophole by חלה? Okay, so it could be,
you know, because it's interesting why the bakery. You could say because,
man, you don't deal with dough in the same scale as you
do with flour, but you say well maybe sometimes you do. So
the גמרא's Gemara going to ask why don't we have a loophole
to close by חלה? So that's exactly the next point. But before
we do that, I do want to also say that,
so the question is, okay, if they're only closing that loophole, there
are two scenarios. One scenario is you grew the grain, you sold
it to the non-Jew, you buy it back. The other scenario is
the non-Jew grows the grain. If you're really concerned, if it's really
just to close this loophole, then you would think that it's the
first case that you're really saying remains חייב, whereas the second case
maybe could be exempt. And also remember even halachically there's a big
difference, when it was grown by the non-Jew, there's the additional argument
that the ownership of the land exempted it. So maybe
we're only going to מחייב m'chayev a case when you sold it
and bought it back and not a case where it all came
from the non-Jew. So תוספות sort of recognizes that as a serious
possibility, but based on other גמרות, Gemoras, he says it sounds like
actually we're saying this דרבנן derabbanan in both cases, that whether it
was grown by the non-Jew, whether it was sold and bought back,
it's the same thing. Whether you owned it, whether you sold it
and bought it back, whether it was all grown by a non-Jew,
because we don't want people subverting the system, we are going to
be מחייב it in תרומות ומעשרות. Okay, so this is actually quite
interesting.
Also not subverting it to the same extent when
it's grown by the non-Jew.
Right, that's right. Those who think it's possible that we shouldn't make
the גזירה there. Those who actually think the logic is you shouldn't
make the גזירה there, but from other גמרות gemaras it sounds like
it's a type of a לא פלוג. lo pelug.
But absolutely, you know, so again, this would be quite... You didn't
buy and sell it, though. We don't say that on שמיטה shemita
because...
Right, so that it is a little bit ironic, you know, because
here we have like I said what this is all bracketing is
the question that non-Jewish ownership exempts. And you know we all live
in this world where we have all these, you know, workarounds. I
mean we just read בהר, Behar, you know, and the whole thing
is well you have the היתר hetter you have the, you know
the פרוזבול, pruzbul, right? What what what do you have by בהר?
Behar? You have first of all okay it's mentioned in this פרשה
parsha it's mentioned in דברים Devarim but you know it's the annulment
of debts. So for that we got the פרוזבול, pruzbul, you have
not lending with interest you got the היתר עסקא, hetter iska, you
have the basic law of שמיטה shemita that you have the היתר
מכירה, right? So here the גמרא Gemara knows that you can actually
get around and is actually making a דרבנן d'rabbanan to close that
loophole. Okay, so that's quite interesting. I just have to say while
we're maybe just, you know, the great joke that somebody once said
that okay so Orthodox, Reform, and Conservative rabbi get together and they
say look you know, or maybe like the leaders of the movements
all get together and they say we agree on so many things
let's at least try to find something we can all agree upon.
So they so they you know spend a lot of time and
they say you know what we can all agree that health that
smoking is bad. You know it's a health concern, from an ethical
issue it's wrong, it injures other people's health. You know there's a
מצוה mitzvah ושמרתם מאוד לנפשותיכם v'shishmartem me'od l'nafshoseichem so we can all
agree that there should be a ban on smoking. So they all
agree. Okay, so then a year later the three leaders of the
movements bump into each other on the street and they're all smoking.
I heard this joke from an Israeli because in Israel everybody smokes.
Anyway,
so they all look at each other, what about what about what
we agreed upon? So the Reform rabbi says well you know actually
at the end of the day although we did all agree upon
it and then you know made the decision in the end we
believe that the working of that body has a vote and not
a veto and in the end it's each person's autonomous decision what
to do. So then they look at the Conservative rabbi says what
about you? He says well you know if you look at the
historical record about exactly how that vote took place and you put
it in the right sort of historical context you'll understand that there's
different ways to interpret it so it was not so clear. So
then they look at the Orthodox rabbi say נו nu what about
you? He says what do you want from me? I sold my
lungs to a גוי. goy.
So there you go.
That's the joke to this week's פרשה. parsha. Anyway.
Okay so alright so so therefore we want to close that loophole
which we are so good at getting at finding those loopholes. So
the גמרא says what? Except for עגונה? aguna? Except for עגונה. aguna.
Okay. Okay so there you go. Alright, אי הכי ei hachi okay
point taken. אי הכי ei hachi אפילו חלה נמי? afilu challah nami?
So the גמרא says why do you have to close the loophole
for חלה? Why do you allow the ownership of the non-Jew to
continue to exempt for חלה? So the גמרא says no there
we there you're gonna always have a loophole anyway. Even if we
try to close the loophole you'll always have a way to get
out of it if you want to get out of it. Which
is what? אפשר דאפיה פחות מחמשת רבעים
קמח ועוד. efshar d'afyei pachos mechameshes reva'im kemach v'od. There you can
bake the flour made from less than the full שיעור shiur that's
חייב in חלה which is five רבעים reva'im which is a certain
measure of bread and a little bit more. Right? Yeah I'm not
going to get into exactly what that measure is but the point
is if you wanted to get out of it then even if
we close the loophole of the non-Jew you could get out of
it anyway you could make less. But here there's a huge loophole
and if we don't close this you're not going to get out
of this so we had to close it. So the גמרא says
one minute תרומה נמי אפשר דעביד ליה כדרבי אושעיא. teruma nami efshar
d'avid lei k'rabbi oshaya.
What do you mean? If a person is looking for a loophole
even if you close this area they can still get out of
it like רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya. What does רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya
teach? דאמר רבי אושעיא d'amar Rabbi Oshaya מערים אדם על תבואתו ומכניסה
במוץ שלה כדי שתהא בהמה אוכלת ופטורה מן המעשר. m'arim adam al
tevuaso u-machnisa b'motz shelah k'dei she'tei behema ocheles u-ptura min ha-ma'aser.
רבי אושעיא Rabbi Oshaya says the following: when is the grain חייב
in מעשר? We spoke about מירוח. The מירוח happens after you winnow
it and get the get all the מוץ motz out and then
you smooth it over in the pile. So he says if you
take it into the house with the מוץ motz then it's only
חייב actually what's called ראיית פני הבית. re'iyas p'nei habayis. It's been
winnowed the מוץ motz has been removed and then it's brought into
the house to the threshing floor wherever you know into the barn.
So here if you brought inside with the מוץ motz still on
it then it never becomes obligated because it never was brought inside
after having been processed. And therefore you can continue to feed it
to your animal and there are no restrictions. So therefore if you
really wanted to get out of it you you could do it
without selling to a non-Jew you do it this way. אי נמי
ei nami or the גמרא says דאעילה דרך גגות ודרך קרפיפות. d'ayeila
derech gaggos v'derech karpifos.
So it's only חייב when you bring it into the house in
the normal way. If you get it into the house through the
roof or through the קרפיף karpif whatever that is some type of
a I don't know back door or something then in those types
of a case you are not חייב. So if you really wanted
to get out of it there's other ways you could try. trick
and get out of it. So why do we have to close
this other loophole of the non-Jews? There are these existing loopholes if
you really wanted to get out of it.
So the גמרא says no. התם בפרהסיא זילא בה מילתא. Hasam b'farhesia
zeila bah milta. There, it's very public, right? If people see you
lowering your grain down through the roof or they see you bringing
it in and not doing the winnowing out in the field, they're
going to say oh, this guy's cheating the system, he's getting out
of מעשר, it's very public. So therefore people don't use that loophole
as much. The non-Jew would be a huge loophole that people would
use that would not be so public, nobody would see me lowering
my, you know, it's a private transaction selling it to the non-Jew.
So that's a loophole that we really have to close. And דהכא
בצנעא לא זילא בה מילתא. v'hacha b'tzina lo zeila bah milta.
Also says the גמרא by the flour, using the way רש"י would.
בצנעא tzina could refer to the non-Jew case, selling it to a
non-Jew is private, or it could refer to the dough. If I
want to make less than the שיעור of dough, it's also something
I can do privately. So if I wanted to get out of
my obligation, if I can do it in private, I will. If
I have to publicly announce what a cheat I am, I'm not
going to do it. Okay, so therefore we have to close. By
flour you'll always have a way to get out of it by
dough, so it doesn't do us any good to close a loophole.
But here you don't have a private, the only private way to
get out of it is through selling it to a non-Jew and
that's the loophole that we have to close.
Yes. One for תרומה terumah? all the time, but apparently the rules
are the same for מעשר, right? One for...
Yeah, I think some of it said תרומות ומעשרות, didn't it? Did
it all say תרומה?
terumah I mean the משנה Mishnah. said מעשר, פטור מן המעשרות. patur
min ha'ma'asrot. And then when it was introduced it says תורמי מיניה.
tormei minei. There,
like that was, I think the next משנה Mishnah was about תרומות,
but there's something here תרומות ומעשרות are all the same thing. Okay.
For תרומה לא לימצא זיופא. lo limtza ziyufa.
Right, that's throughout. Right, the big loophole is for מעשר which is
ten percent, and then שני מעשרות shnei ma'asrot is twenty percent, so
you understand people want to get out of it. Okay, great. So
let that be the next משנה. Mishnah So that deals with the
whole תרומות ומעשרות case and closing off those loopholes. So here's the
משנה. Mishnah. So now you have winnowed the grain, you winnowed the
flour... if the remainder you've redeemed and sold off, פטור patur in
מעשר, not פטור patur in חלה for reasons we said. Back to
making the עומר. Omer בא
לו לעשרון. ba lo l'isaron. So now you've come to your עשרון
that was left over, the amount that you're actually going to make
or that you kept, the amount you're actually going to make the
עומר Omer... out of. נתן עליו שמנה ולבונתה. natan alav shamnah u'levonatah.
You put the oil and the לבונה levonah on it. The order
is completely out of order here. Let me just read it and
then I'll try to tell you what the right order is. יצק,
yatzak, you write, you pour the oil ובלל, u'balal, you mixed it
with the oil.
הניף והגיש, henif v'higish, you did the תנופה tenufah and the הגשה.
hagashah. Okay, that actually is the right order because the משנה Mishnah.
before told that all מנחות menachot have both תנופה tenufah and הגשה,
hagashah, that תנופה tenufah comes first if I read correctly.
Let
me see. Hold on a second.
Yeah, on ס"א samech-aleph it says the משנה says where was it?
תנופה
קודמת
להגשה.
tenufah
kodemet
l'hagashah.
So you do the תנופה tenufah before the הגשה. hagashah. So that
order is correct. קמץ, kamatz, you do the קמיצה. kemitza. This is
a normal מנחה. mincha. והקטיר, v'hiktir, you burn up the קומץ kometz
on the altar. והשאר נאכל לכהנים. v'hash'ar ne'echal l'kohanim. The rest is
eaten by the כהנים. kohanim. The normal מנחה. mincha. I know. We'll
talk about the first half of the משנה. Let's finish the משנה.
Now here, משקרב העומר, mishekarav ha'Omer, once the עומר Omer, was brought,
יוצאין, yotzin, you would leave the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash ומוצאין שוקי
ירושלים... u'motzin shukei Yerushalayim... שוקי שוקי... shukei shukei... ירושלים... Yerushalayim... שהוא מלא
קמח קלי. she'hu malei kemach kali. You found as soon as you
walked out of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash all of the marketplaces
were bringing out and they were selling roasted grain because now it's
מותר mutar to eat the new grain. Okay, so now everybody, you
know, as soon as it was brought everybody would start selling roasted
grain. Now שלא ברצון
חכמים, shelo birtzon chachamim, not with the approval of the sages. Why
not? דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. In order to be selling
the grain as soon as the עומר Omer is brought, you have
to have cut the grain beforehand. Okay, now there's two questions. Number
one is you're handling the grain beforehand and you have to have
cut it before, so A, you're not allowed to cut anything prior
to the cutting of the עומר... לתת בו חרמש. latet bo chermesh.
What? There's וביום הקצרכם. u'v'yom haktzirchem.
No,
but there's also ראשית קצירכם. reishit ktzirchem. So if you cut before
the עומר, you are impinging on its status of ראשית קצירכם. reishit
ktzirchem. It's not the same like the לאו lav of eating חדש,
chadash, but you're impinging on its status of ראשית קצירכם. reishit ktzirchem.
So number one is you're not allowed to cut. So the גמרא
is going to say okay, you're not allowed to cut, but there
were these people that did it, they did it through using their
hands and picking it and not cutting it, that was allowed.
But the other thing that the rabbis didn't like... and the night
before?
Right, maybe could that be... an interesting question which the גמרא doesn't
deal with, I have to check on that. I was wondering about
that. What if the cutting occurred after the first cutting but before
it was actually brought? The גמרא actually assumes, as we'll see tomorrow,
that even then you had to use your hand, so it seems
like it's saying that until it's brought. But I'll double check that.
Anyway, the other thing is you're handling this חדש chadash and you're
getting it all ready to eat while it's still אסור. assur. Are
we concerned that you accidentally might come to eat for it before
the עומר is brought? So it said that was שלא ברצון חכמים,
shelo birtzon chachamim, דברי רבי מאיר. רבי יהודה אומר ברצון חכמים היו
עושים. Rabbi Yehuda omer birtzon chachamim hayu osim. No, the חכמים chachamim
were... were okay with it, and we're going to see why in
the גמרא *Gemara*. Just one statement about the order: so the תנופה
*Tenufa* and the הגשה *Hagasha* was right, but yes, everything else was
wrong. First of all, you don't want to put on the לבונה
*Levona* before you've mixed it all together, because the לבונה *Levona* has
to remain separate and has to come off. The לבונה *Levona* is
instead put on at the last. Also the order, as the גמרא
*Gemara* says, is first you put the שמן *Shemen* in the כלי
*Kli*, then you put the oil in, then you put in more,
then you put the flour in, then you put in more oil,
then you mix it and then you do a final יציקה *Yetzika*.
So the actual correct order would be נתן עליה שמנה *Natan Aleha
Shamno*. The שמן *Shemen* is not on first, it's נתן *Natan* שמן
*Shemen* in the כלי *Kli*. So let me know, right? And unless
עליה *Aleha* means the כלי *Kli*, you totally bracket the לבונה *Levona*.
יצק *Yatzak* is wrong, it really is בלל *Balal*. You add more
oil, you בלל *Balal*, and then you do יציקה *Yetzika* at the
last. Why is it all wrong? I have no idea. רש"י *Rashi*
and תוספות *Tosfos* both point out that the order is completely wrong,
it was just a short way of saying. Okay, tomorrow we will
see the issue about whether handling the grain before the absolute, before
it actually becomes מותר *Mutar*.